ALI LARA

alilarag@mail.com • (614) 440-6494 • aliglara @ Linkedin • Austin, TX

SUMMARY

Analytical mindset, having extensive experience extracting useful facts from data. Enjoy open-ended issues and the application of developing technologies to challenging cases in various sectors. Good communicator with an optimistic outlook and a desire to solve problems

EXPERIENCE

Process Assistant, Amazon, Austin, TX

Mar 2023 - present

- Streamlined the workflow established by the leading team to improve the performance of our team in a safe environment
- Implemented the daily workflow to ensure the performance of L1-team is efficient and cost-effective in a safe environment
- Led a 35-member team aimed at developing an effective inbound system for 70k+ packages daily
- Employ quantitative analytical real-time tools to monitor the manufacturing process
- Performed continuous evaluation of work methods, procedures, and policies and made recommendations for improvements to the leadership team

Yard Marshal, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Dec 2021 - Mar 2023

- Daily construction and maintenance of an inbound/outbound workflow to ensure a continuous site operation
- Led a 10-member team aimed at developing efficient loading/unloading system for 40k+ of packages daily
- Communicated with both dispatches and inbound/outbound drivers to ensure on-time arrivals and departures
- Analytically managed physical and virtual check-in procedures for an average of 15 linehauls to guarantee they could be unloaded safely and escalated any safety concerns to management
- Conducted daily audits on the dock to assure strict adherence to Amazon procedures as well as local and DOT safety regulations
- Maintained and updated electronic and hard copy records of inbound and outbound deliveries in real-time

FC Associate, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Nov 2020 - Dec 2021

- Increased the average rate from under 200 units per hour by 40% or greater by coaching under-performing associates daily to meet production goals and exceeded standards
- Exceed over 379 expected UPH, while the building average stow rate was 250, 500+ was reached which represents being at the 95th percentile
- Processed hazardous materials following all federal and local EPA/RCRA standards for handling, classifying and shipping hazardous waste
- Processed damaged packages for repacking, hazmat, returns, and third-party contractor shipping
- Coached Day-1 and Week-1 associates to orient them to the station layout, standards of work, and safety culture

Machine Learning Engineer II, MCL Control, Venezuela

May 2012 - Sep 2019

- Served as Team Leader from design to execution of machine learning algorithms to develop predictive models and optimize the performance of advanced control process algorithms for rotary industrial machinery
- Managed data-driven solutions team of three researchers, identified vulnerabilities, tested solutions, established standardized workflow, and executed programs in oil/gas industry
- Constructed neural network models in Python/Tensorflow to estimate theorical physical parameters required by process simulations built on Aspen Hysys to improve the application performance
- Managed a 10-junior engineers' team over a one-year period and coached them on using XGBoost and random forest models to optimize the feature selection, via ROC/AUC metrics, for proposed machine learning solutions
- Executed more than five process simulation models per year, performing optimization studies, and preparing technical papers and presentations
- Gathered information, identified analytical requirements, and developed data-driven based models to translate complex business needs into actionable analytic projects
- Developed an assistive tool to perform HAZOP studies based on autoregressive models and machine learning techniques in compliance with design specifications
- Designed and implemented machine learning models to detect problems and predict failures using deep learning techniques, primarily for turbo-compressors and turbofans

Researcher, Universidad Central of Venezuela, Venezuela

Mar 2005 – Nov 2020

- Researched chemical reaction engineering, mathematical modeling, simulation and optimization, process synthesis and design including economic assessments, process integration, and machine learning techniques for industrial process evaluation
- Lectured in several chemical engineering areas including thermodynamics, chemical reactor design, numerical methods, industrial process simulation, and statistical modeling
- Implemented a problem-solved learning experience in different subjects following the ABET guidance.
- Coached 200+ chemical engineering undergraduates with regards to academic pathways and toward degree completion and established and provided career counseling for a network of cooperatives, internships, and externships to foster academic to industry pipeline
- Mentored students throughout the process, developed semesterly goals and advised on study abroad opportunities based on the double-degree program of the Politecnico di Torino, and Sapienza University of Rome (Italy), IFP School (France), IESA School of Management (Venezuela), and Florida International University (USA)

EDUCATION

DataCamp.com, Python for Data Scientist

Universidad Central of Venezuela, M.Sc. Chemical Engineering

2005 – 2008

Universidad Central of Venezuela, B.Sc. Chemical Engineering

1990 – 1998

SKILLS

- Process modeling: Statistical modeling, Matlab, Hysys
- Data Analysis: Excel, SQL, noSQL, Tableau
- Machine learning: Python, R, Tensorflow